<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Releases | FW/1 - The Invisible Framework]]></title>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/categories/releases/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-06-21T12:26:17-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://framework-one.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 2.5 Is Released!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2014/05/25/fw1-2-5-is-released/"/>
    <updated>2014-05-25T23:13:39-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2014/05/25/fw1-2-5-is-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is a migration release to pave the way for breaking changes in Release 3.0. All examples have been updated to latest best practices and now use cfcscript exclusively. Examples use DI/1 0.5.0 to manage all beans and services (as <code>framework.ioc</code>), and no longer rely on start/end actions or the <code>service()</code> method.<!-- more --></p>

<p>As always, FW/1 can be downloaded from the <a href="http://fw1.riaforge.org">FW/1 page on RIAForge</a>. Release 2.5 is now the latest stable release of this framework, as it approaches its fifth birthday!</p>

<p>For a full list of all tickets closed in Release 2.5: <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?milestone=14&amp;page=1&amp;state=closed">https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?milestone=14&amp;page=1&amp;state=closed</a></p>

<h2>Migration from 2.2.1</h2>

<p>The <code>service()</code> call has been deprecated, as have start/end action items. Global access to <code>rc</code> in <code>Application.cfc</code> has also been deprecated. If you just drop 2.5 into your setup and you rely on these features, you&rsquo;ll get exceptions explaining how to enable these features for backward compatibility, namely add the following to your framework configuration:</p>

<pre><code>enableGlobalRC = true,
suppressServiceQueue = false
</code></pre>

<p>The ability to enable the implicit service calls is still present via:</p>

<pre><code>suppressImplicitService = false
</code></pre>

<p>but, like the other two options, defaults to disallowing the deprecated feature.</p>

<p>If you enable these deprecated features, you will no longer get exceptions using them, but you will see deprecation warnings in your application server&rsquo;s console log. This is to remind you to update your code in preparation for 3.0 later this year!</p>

<p><em>Please note that Release 3.0 will completely remove these backward compatibility options &ndash; and the associated deprecated features. In addition, <code>org.corfield.framework</code> will move to <code>framework.one</code> in Release 3.0, alongside <code>framework.ioc</code>.</em></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 2.2 Released!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2013/12/18/fw1-2-2-released/"/>
    <updated>2013-12-18T22:34:03-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2013/12/18/fw1-2-2-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Framework One version 2.2 is now available for production use! You can download it from the <a href="http://fw1.riaforge.org/">Framework One page on RIAForge</a>. This includes one bug fix over RC2 (interaction between <code>renderData()</code> and trace output).<!-- more --></p>

<p>The main focus of the 2.2 release is improved support for REST APIs, through the addition of <code>renderData()</code> to simplify returning JSON, XML and plain text results to the caller, as well as more sophisticated route handling via &ldquo;resource packs&rdquo; which let you define a family of related routes for a given resource type, using a shorthand notation. For more information, see this <a href="http://corfield.org/blog/post.cfm/fw-1-releases-and-roadmap">blog post about the latest FW/1 release and the roadmap</a>.</p>

<p>As noted previously, the master branch is the current stable release (2.2), and the develop branch has become the next release (2.5). 2.5 will be released next month and will be a stepping stone toward some substantial changes coming in 3.0. For more detail, read this <a href="/blog/2013/11/02/fw1-the-year-ahead">blog post explaining the changes coming in 2.5 and 3.0</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
