<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Releases | FW/1 - The Invisible Framework]]></title>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/categories/releases/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-09-06T22:58:57-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://framework-one.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 New Releases Etc]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/06/fw1-news/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-06T22:25:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/06/fw1-news</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>A couple of months have passed since <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/07/12/fw1-3-1-released/">FW/1 3.1 was released</a> but things have been busy behind the scenes!</p>

<p>As indicated in July, work on FW/1 3.5 had been progressing in parallel (the first time two releases of FW/1 have been worked on concurrently!) and you can already download <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0-alpha2">FW/1 3.5 Alpha 2</a>.
Yes, there was an <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0-alpha1">Alpha 1</a> as well, but as work progressed on the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/3.5/">massively overhauled 3.5 documentation</a>, some important usability enhancements
appeared and a new alpha was released within 24 hours! In particular, the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/3.5/cfml-and-clojure.html">Clojure and CFML Sitting in a Tree</a> section has been extensively updated and includes a fully worked example of
how to create FW/1 application from scratch using the REPL to create Clojure services and controllers, with CFML views and layouts!</p>

<p>You’ll also probably notice that the FW/1 website has had a facelift, finally getting the look’n’feel that Kevin Stannard designed five years ago. Better late than never, and huge thanks to Kevin again for his wonderful logo design and choice of colors!
The 3.5 documentation now includes a table of contents on each page, making it easier to navigate (this will probably get backported to 3.1 and 3.0 at some point).</p>

<p>In addition to the ongoing work on FW/1 3.5, we also have an <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.1.1">important bug fix release for the 3.1.x version</a> which addresses a potential problem with REST APIs.</p>

<p>Finally, if you’re a <a href="https://www.ortussolutions.com/products/commandbox">CommandBox</a> fan, we have good news: you can now easily install FW/1 3.1.2 and 3.5.0 (prerelease) via <code>box</code>. I’ll be blogging about this shortly. The 3.1.2 release is exactly the same as 3.1.1 (including the version number!)
but it includes <code>box.json</code> for compatibility with ForgeBox / CommandBox. In addition, Tony Junkes has contributed an <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1-commands">initial set of <code>box</code> commands for FW/1</a> that let you get up and running quickly. This will be covered in the next blog post.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.1 Released!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/07/12/fw1-3-1-released/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-12T20:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/07/12/fw1-3-1-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The “gold” release of FW/1 3.1 (3.1.0) is now available for production use! You can <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.1.0">download FW/1 3.1.0 from GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>FW 3.1 is a maintenance release of the 3.x series, containing a number of bug fixes and enhancements. The main new feature of release 3.1 is the addition of AOP/1, thanks to the tireless work of <a href="https://github.com/dbudde">Daniel Budde</a>.<!--more--></p>

<h2 id="aop1">AOP/1</h2>
<p>AOP/1 brings Aspect-Oriented Programming to FW/1 applications by extending the capabilities of DI/1 with “interceptors” that can be automatically woven into your beans to allow you to call additional methods before, after, or instead of (“around”) the native methods on your beans.
Please read <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/using-aop-one.html">the all new AOP/1 documentation</a> provided by Daniel Budde for more details on how to use this powerful new feature.</p>

<h2 id="enhancements">Enhancements</h2>

<ul>
  <li><code>renderData()</code> now supports both <code>html</code>, <code>rawjson</code> and <code>jsonp</code> data types.</li>
  <li><code>redirect()</code> now supports a <code>header</code> argument to allow for custom redirect-like behavior such as might be needed in a Single-Page-Application or heavy ajax usage.</li>
  <li>Routes:
    <ul>
      <li>Regex support for <code>^</code> to anchor the match to the start of the request string.</li>
      <li>Placeholders can now have matches restricted by regex patterns (e.g., to match numeric-only portions of the request string).</li>
      <li>Regex matching can now be made case-sensitive via the new <code>routesCaseSensitive</code> option.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Per-subsystem configuration now supports <code>diEngine</code>, <code>diComponent</code>, <code>diLocations</code>, and <code>diConfig</code>.</li>
  <li>Per-environment configuration is now merged recursively, including appropriate parts of <code>diConfig</code>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="bug-fixes">Bug Fixes</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Route matching for placeholders was too eager. Placeholder names are now restricted to alphanumeric plus <code>_</code> and <code>-</code> characters only. <em>This is potentially a breaking change if you have used unusual characters in placeholder variable names that are legal in CFML identifiers!</em></li>
  <li>If the first request to an application was also a reload request, initialization was sometimes attempted twice if an exception was thrown during initialization.</li>
  <li>Framework reloads were not always thread safe and could produce strange behavior if an application was reloaded under load.</li>
  <li>DI/1’s <code>isConstant()</code> method could fail for manually created and managed beans.</li>
  <li><code>Application.cfc</code> was not always correctly autowired as a Controller.</li>
  <li>If content had been produced in a request that used <code>renderData()</code>, that content could corrupt the result. A content reset is now performed in such cases.</li>
  <li>DI/1 no longer attempts to instantiate interfaces that it discovers in the model.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="platform-support">Platform Support</h2>

<ul>
  <li>ColdFusion 9.0.1 and Railo 4.0 are no longer officially supported by FW/1. FW/1 3.1 applications will probably still run on them but there are some bugs in both engine versions that can impact some of the new functionality in this release.
FW/1 3.1 officially supports ColdFusion 9.0.2 or later, Railo 4.1 or later, and Lucee 4.5.1.000 or later.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="code-of-conduct">Code of Conduct</h2>
<p>As part of my commitment to diversity in IT, Framework One now has a <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/blob/master/CODE_OF_CONDUCT.md">Code of Conduct</a> that encompasses all aspects of interaction with the project: on GitHub, on the mailing list, and in presentations given by community members to promote the framework.
This brings Framework in line with a number of progressive open source projects that have adopted a Code of Conduct as a way to make the open source software community more welcoming and more inclusive.</p>

<h2 id="contributors">Contributors</h2>
<p>The star contributor for this release is <a href="https://github.com/dbudde">Daniel Budde</a> for rewriting AOP/1 (twice!) so it is ready for inclusion with FW/1! Thank you!</p>

<p>Other contributors, in alphabetical order of GitHub name:</p>

<ul>
  <li>atuttle - Adam Tuttle</li>
  <li>cybersonic - Mark Drew</li>
  <li>GiancarloGomez - Giancarlo Gomez</li>
  <li>guillaume-boivin - Guillaume Boivin</li>
  <li>jcberquist - John Berquist</li>
  <li>jochemd - Jochem van Dieten</li>
  <li>Ronner</li>
  <li>ryanguill - Ryan Guill</li>
</ul>

<p>And, yeah, I did a bit too, but FW/1 wouldn’t be where it is today without contributions from the open source CFML community - thank you everyone!</p>

<h2 id="additional-information">Additional Information</h2>
<p>For a complete list of changes since 3.0:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Issues Closed</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Pull Requests Merged</a></li>
</ul>

<p>Release 3.5 Alpha 1 will follow shortly, with a focus on language integration, bringing
automatic support for Clojure code in the Model and Controllers, as well as first class support for the Lucee Language in the Model, the Views, and the Controllers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.1 Release Candidate 2 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/07/07/fw1-3-1-rc-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-07-07T16:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/07/07/fw1-3-1-rc-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second Release Candidate of FW/1 3.1 is now available for testing. You <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.1-rc2">download FW/1 3.1 RC 2 from GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>These are the changes since RC 1:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Major overhaul of AOP/1; intercept by CFC type; intercept by CFC name regex (Daniel Budde).</li>
  <li>Routes now support regex restriction on placeholder variables (Guillaume Boivin).</li>
</ul>

<p>For a complete list of changes since 3.0:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Issues Closed</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Pull Requests Merged</a></li>
</ul>

<p>At this point, release 3.1 should be considered “production ready” and only critical bug fixes will be included between now and the “gold” release. It is the default download on RIAForge and will be merged to master tomorrow in preparation for the final release at the weekend.</p>

<p>As noted before, release 3.5 will follow fairly quickly after that, with a focus on language integration, bringing
automatic support for Clojure code in the Model and Controllers, as well as first class support for the Lucee Language in the Model, the Views, and the Controllers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.1 Release Candidate 1 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/06/28/fw1-3-1-rc-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-28T17:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/06/28/fw1-3-1-rc-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The first Release Candidate of FW/1 3.1 is now available for testing. You <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.1-rc1">download FW/1 3.1 RC 1 from GitHub</a>.</p>

<p>These are the changes since Beta 2:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code>renderData()</code> supports <code>"jsonp"</code> (Giancarlo Gomez) and <code>"html"</code>.</li>
  <li><code>renderData()</code> now causes a content reset before rendering the data (Giancarlo Gomez).</li>
  <li>Subsystem-specific configuration can now override <code>diEngine</code>, <code>diLocations</code>, and <code>diComponent</code>. Previously it could only override <code>diConfig</code>.</li>
  <li><code>setupApplication()</code> no longer runs twice when first request is also a reload request.</li>
</ul>

<p>For a complete list of changes since 3.0:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Issues Closed</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.1">Pull Requests Merged</a></li>
</ul>

<p>At this point, release 3.1 is “feature complete” and only bug fixes will be included between now and the “gold” release. Release 3.5 will follow fairly quickly after that, with a focus on language integration, bringing
automatic support for Clojure code in the Model and Controllers, as well as first class support for the Lucee Language in the Model, the Views, and the Controllers.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.1 Beta 2 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/fw1-3-1-beta-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-06-20T00:59:49-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/06/20/fw1-3-1-beta-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The second beta version of FW/1 3.1 is available for testing. Whilst this is a minor bug fix and enhancement release, it now includes the first major rewrite of AOP/1. Documentation will follow shortly. Massive thanks to Daniel Budde for the rewrite! You can <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.1-beta2">download FW/1 3.1 Beta 2</a> from GitHub, as well as read the full release notes there.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
