<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Releases | FW/1 - The Invisible Framework]]></title>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/categories/releases/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2016-07-26T12:06:34-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://framework-one.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 4.0.0 Release Candidate 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/26/fw1-4-0-0-rc-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-26T12:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/26/fw1-4-0-0-rc-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v4.0.0-rc1">FW/1 4.0.0 RC 1</a> is available.
The only change from Beta 2 is a bug fix in the handling of load listeners for subsystem bean factories (the default load listener is no longer inherited).</p>

<p>For full details, read the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/4.0/changes.html">Change Log for FW/1 4.0</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 4.0.0 Beta 2]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/12/fw1-4-0-0-beta-2/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-12T12:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/12/fw1-4-0-0-beta-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v4.0.0-beta2">FW/1 4.0.0 Beta 2</a> is available.
The only change from Beta 1 is that the <code>enableJSONPOST</code> setting has been renamed to <code>decodeRequestBody</code>.
This is a <strong>breaking change</strong> if you were using that setting in the earlier Alpha / Beta builds:
you will now get an exception and will need to update your application’s configuration.</p>

<p>For full details, read the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/4.0/changes.html">Change Log for FW/1 4.0</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 4.0.0 Beta 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/11/fw1-4-0-0-beta-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-07-11T14:45:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/07/11/fw1-4-0-0-beta-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v4.0.0-beta1">FW/1 4.0.0 Beta 1</a> is available.
Per those release notes, the beta contains a small number of enhancements and bug fixes since Alpha 1 was released in March.</p>

<p>For full details, read the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/4.0/changes.html">Change Log for FW/1 4.0</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 4.0.0 Alpha 1]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/03/05/fw1-4-0-0-alpha-1/"/>
    <updated>2016-03-05T17:00:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/03/05/fw1-4-0-0-alpha-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v4.0.0-alpha1">FW/1 4.0.0 Alpha 1</a> is available. At this point FW/1 4.0.0 is feature complete – there may be a few very minor changes between now and the Beta, and then only bug fixes through the RC phase. We’ve been using this <strong>develop</strong> version in production at work all along so I consider it solid enough for serious work.<!-- more --></p>

<p>The focus of the 4.0 release is on improving REST support. Improvements include:</p>

<ul>
  <li>JSON-encoded POST body support.</li>
  <li>Controllers have easy access to HTTP headers.</li>
  <li>Builder syntax for <code>renderData()</code> result elements.</li>
  <li>Support for user-supplied rendering functions.</li>
  <li>Integrated support for HTTP <code>OPTIONS</code> verb.</li>
  <li>Per-resource error handling.</li>
  <li>Setting status text (in addition to status code) in HTTP responses.</li>
  <li>Wildcard HTTP method support.</li>
</ul>

<p>In addition, DI/1 has had a number of enhancements, including the addition of a builder syntax for programmatically declaring beans.</p>

<p>For more detail, read the <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/4.0/changes.html">Change Log for FW/1 4.0</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 4.0 and Beyond]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/01/05/fw1-4-0-and-beyond/"/>
    <updated>2016-01-05T22:20:00-08:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2016/01/05/fw1-4-0-and-beyond</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Happy New Year and Welcome to 2016!</p>

<p>FW/1 3.5 has been out for a few months now and I want to talk about what’s coming this year.<!-- more -->
FW/1 4.0 is well under way and the themes are REST APIs and enhancements to DI/1. You can read <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/4.0/changes.html">the FW/1 4.0 change log</a> here to see how much has been done so far. There are <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aopen+is%3Aissue+milestone%3A4.0">only a few issues left for 4.0</a> so we’re close to the first Alpha release at this point.</p>

<p>Why the 4.0 version? A major version number change indicates breaking changes. 4.0 drops support for Adobe ColdFusion 9.0.x because it relies on closures. Frankly, I’d like to drop support for Adobe ColdFusion 10 so I could rely on using member functions, but I feel it’s important to support two major versions. Just bear in mind that Raijin – ColdFusion 2016 – is coming and when that’s released, I will drop support for ACF10!</p>

<p>Aside from the minimum version support, FW/1 4.0 includes a (potentially) breaking change around <code>property</code> declarations: if a <code>property</code> includes a type or default, it will no longer be considered for injection. In FW/1 3.5, typed properties could be excluded if you specified <code>omitTypedProperties : true</code>. That is the default in 4.0 so you can still restore the earlier behavior. In addition, 4.0 now ignores defaulted properties but you can specify <code>omitDefaultedProperties : false</code> to override that new behavior.</p>

<p>The next planned version of FW/1 will be 4.5 – a fairly major release that will pave the way for 5.0, in the same way 2.5 paved the way for 3.0. In 5.0, the request lifecycle methods will move from <code>Application.cfc</code> (or your custom CFC that extends <code>framework.one</code> in the <strong>Alternative Application Structure</strong>) to a separate CFC, and subsystems will also be able to specify a request lifecycle with a <code>subsystem.cfc</code> – and subsystems with such a CFC will be eagerly loaded at application startup (whereas subsystems are lazily loaded today). In order to provide a smooth upgrade path, FW/1 4.5 will support most of those features but disabled by default and will provide warnings or throw exceptions if the behavior would change in 5.0.</p>

<p>As always, I want FW/1 to be driven by your needs so please raise issues on the <a href="http://groups.google.com/group/framework-one/">mailing list</a> or on <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1">GitHub</a> so that your voices are heard and can drive future versions of one of CFML’s most popular MVC/DI/AOP frameworks!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
