<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Fw1 | FW/1 - The Invisible Framework]]></title>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/categories/fw1/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2015-11-20T16:54:21-08:00</updated>
  <id>http://framework-one.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Sean Corfield]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.5.0 Released!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/10/21/fw1-3-5-0-released/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-21T12:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/10/21/fw1-3-5-0-released</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0">Gold Release of FW/1 3.5.0</a> is available for general release and production use. The focus of this release is integration, bringing an improved way to add subsystems to an existing application, an easier way to add FW/1 to a legacy application, support for mixed CFML / Clojure applications, better support for WireBox, and full support for ForgeBox and CommandBox!<!-- more --></p>

<p>The major new features in FW/1 3.5.0 are:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Subsystems 2.0. A new, more streamlined way to add subsystems to an existing FW/1 application has been added. Thank you to <a href="https://github.com/sneiland">Steven Neiland</a> for the inspiration and guiding principles! Read about <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/using-subsystems.html">Subsystems 2.0</a> and how they differ from the older approach (which is still supported). The examples have been reworked to use Subsystems 2.0 so you can see how it works in practice.</li>
  <li>An <strong>Alternative Application Structure</strong> is now supported that allows you to create FW/1 applications that do not require <code>Application.cfc</code> extends the FW/1 component. Read about <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/developing-applications.html#alternative-application-structure">the Alternative Application Structure</a>. Some of the examples have been updated to use this approach so you can see how it works in practice.</li>
  <li>Clojure integration. If you have Leiningen installed (Clojure’s build tool) then it is very easy to write services and/or controllers in Clojure and have FW/1 automatically integrate those into your CFML application. Read about <a href="http://framework-one.github.io/documentation/cfml-and-clojure.html">mixing CFML &amp; Clojure</a> for more details. An example of Clojure integration is provided in the repository (you’ll need <a href="http://leiningen.org">Leiningen</a> installed for that example to run).</li>
  <li>ForgeBox / CommandBox support. FW/1 now has a <code>box.json</code> file and is hosted on ForgeBox so it can be easily installed via CommandBox.</li>
</ul>

<p>In addition to the major features, the following enhancements have been added:</p>

<ul>
  <li><code>redirect()</code> allows <code>queryString</code> to be a struct, like <code>buildURL()</code>.</li>
  <li><code>isFrameworkReloadRequest()</code> is now public in case an application needs to take action when the framework is reloaded.</li>
  <li><code>getSubsystemSectionAndItem()</code> added to supplement <code>getFullyQualifiedAction()</code> (the latter omits the subsystem if it is empty).</li>
  <li>The WireBox adapter now supports custom binders.</li>
  <li>The conventions used for various folder names can now be overridden in the framework configuration.</li>
</ul>

<p>And the following bugs have been fixed:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues/377">377</a> - AOP/1 now allows a single interceptor to be applied to multiple objects.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues/361">361</a> - <code>renderData()</code> could kill sessions (this was backported to 3.1.1).</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues/336">336</a> - account for <code>expandPath()</code> returning the wrong directory on ACF11 when the path has a trailing <code>/</code>.</li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, FW/1 includes experimental support for Lucee Language, so if you are running a prerelease build of Lucee Server that has Lucee Language support enabled, you can write controllers and views etc in <code>.lc</code> or <code>.lucee</code> files and FW/1 will use them.</p>

<p>You can read the <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A3.5+is%3Aclosed">full list of changes since 3.1</a> on GitHub, along with
<a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.5">accepted pull requests since 3.1</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.5.0 Release Candidate 2 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/10/06/fw1-3-5-0-rc-2/"/>
    <updated>2015-10-06T15:40:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/10/06/fw1-3-5-0-rc-2</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0-rc2">second Release Candidate of FW/1 3.5.0</a> is available for testing.</p>

<p>This Release Candidate contains a few bug fixes discovered since Release Candidate 1 and is now the <a href="http://fw1.riaforge.org">default download from FW/1’s RIAForge page</a>.
I consider this stable enough to evaluate for production usage at this point – I expect this RC to be the Gold Release unless end user testing uncovers a showstopping issue in the next week or two!</p>

<p>You can read the <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A3.5+is%3Aclosed">full list of changes since 3.1</a> on GitHub, along with
<a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/pulls?q=is%3Apr+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A3.5">accepted pull requests since 3.1</a>..</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.5.0 Release Candidate 1 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/22/fw1-3-5-0-rc-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-22T12:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/22/fw1-3-5-0-rc-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0-rc1">first Release Candidate of FW/1 3.5.0</a> is available for testing.</p>

<p>This Release Candidate contains just bug fixes since Beta 2. Beta 2 contained mostly bug fixes since Beta 1, with one small enhancement to DI/1 (<code>liberal</code> plural support, e.g., <code>libraries</code> becomes <code>library</code>).</p>

<p>You can read the <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A3.5+is%3Aclosed">full list of changes since 3.1</a> on GitHub.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 3.5.0 Beta 1 Available!]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/10/fw1-3-5-0-beta-1/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-10T13:35:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/10/fw1-3-5-0-beta-1</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>The <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/releases/tag/v3.5.0-beta1">first Beta release of FW/1 3.5.0</a> is available for testing.</p>

<p>The focus of this release is integration:<!--more--></p>

<ul>
  <li>Support for controllers and services to be written in CFML (<code>.cfc</code>), Clojure (<code>.clj</code>), or Lucee (<code>.lucee</code>)</li>
  <li>Support for views and layouts to be written in CFML (<code>.cfm</code>) or Lucee (<code>.lucee</code>)</li>
  <li>Configurable folder names to set your own conventions (for <em>controllers</em>, <em>layouts</em>, <em>subsystems</em>, and <em>views</em>)</li>
  <li>Support for <code>Application.cfc</code> to use FW/1 without extending <code>framework.one</code></li>
  <li>A new, cleaner, more consistent set of conventions for adding subsystems to an existing application</li>
</ul>

<p>You can read the <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A3.5+is%3Aclosed">full list of changes since 3.0</a> on GitHub.</p>

<p>The <a href="/documentation/3.5/">documentation for 3.5</a> has been completely overhauled with complete descriptions of all the new features, as well as many
clarifications and expansions of existing features. In particular, you’ll want to check out:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="/documentation/3.5/developing-applications.html#alternative-application-structure">Alternative Application Structure</a></li>
  <li><a href="/documentation/3.5/using-subsystems.html#subsystems-10-vs-20">Subsystems 1.0 vs 2.0</a></li>
  <li><a href="/documentation/3.5/cfml-and-clojure.html">Using Clojure with CFML</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[FW/1 Out of the Box]]></title>
    <link href="http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/06/out-of-the-box/"/>
    <updated>2015-09-06T23:00:00-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://framework-one.github.io/blog/2015/09/06/out-of-the-box</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>FW/1 is up on <a href="http://www.coldbox.org/forgebox">ForgeBox</a>. ForgeBox is the npm / Maven of the CFML world. If you haven’t heard about it – or you think it’s only for “Box” products – you need to check it out! It’s a repository for CFML projects that can be easily installed via <a href="https://www.ortussolutions.com/products/commandbox">Command Box</a>. Wait! You haven’t heard of that either? Gosh, you’ve got some reading to do! It’ll change the way you do development!</p>

<p>Go get it installed, then read on!<!--more--></p>

<p>Now you have <code>box</code> installed, here’s how to get up and running with FW/1 easily:</p>

<pre><code>&gt; box
CommandBox:mydir&gt; install fw1-commands
... you only need to do this once ...
CommandBox:mydir&gt; mkdir example
CommandBox:mydir&gt; cd example
CommandBox:example&gt; fw1 create app example basic
CommandBox:example&gt; install fw1
... installs stable 3.1.2 version ...
CommandBox:example&gt; start
</code></pre>

<p>At this point it’ll open a browser running your new skeleton FW/1 app. Happy coding!</p>

<p>Note that you don’t need to have installed a CFML server, or set up a webroot - <code>box</code> can start a CFML server in any directory so you can get up and running quickly!</p>

<p>You can check out the various <a href="https://github.com/framework-one/fw1-commands">FW/1 commands</a> available inside <code>box</code> but, like Ruby on Rails, they let you quickly add new controllers, views, subsystems and so on to your application. Huge kudos to Tony Junkes for contributing this to the FW/1 family of projects!</p>

<p>Going forward, my plan is that <code>install fw1</code> will always install the current stable (master) version — I just need to remember to keep it up to date! — and you can also install specific versions (currently <code>fw1-3.1.2</code> and <code>fw1-3.5.0</code>). The latter installs from the develop branch. Support for true multiple version installs is planned for <code>box</code>, possibly next month.</p>

<p>One of the things that is really nice about this is you can switch FW/1 versions as easily as:</p>

<pre><code>CommandBox:example&gt; uninstall fw1
CommandBox:example&gt; install fw1-3.5.0
</code></pre>

<p>Now your app is running 3.5.0 (Alpha 2) instead of the stable release!</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
